Operation Lighthouse. re
the unsolved murder of Gail Vella
on September 10th. 2019.
The name we've been given
is Ross Turner.
Enter the property.
5-3. DP for custody
transfer. bringing suspect out now.
Interview of Terry Boyle by
Detective Chief Inspector Davidson.
Mr Boyle. did you shoot Gail Vella?
Did anyone see that?
Armed police! Drop your weapons!
Drop your weapons!
A significant number of other
fingerprints
match an individual identified by
the Police National Computer
as Carl Banks.
Carl Banks has an
extensive history of violence.
including firearms offences.
The person who made me see
that there was another way
to be a useful member of society
was a police officer.
He's the reason why I wanted
to become a police officer too.
To help people.
I can't share any details.
but we might be looking into Vella.
Great. so either I'm accused of
being a traitor
or I become one
to avoid being accused.
We really can't be sure
about the loyalty
of some of these people.
They could banjax the whole thing.
I sent a photo to the handler.
He confirms it's the CHIS.
You're not suggesting
Davidson was involved?
You have no idea
what she's capable of.
It's over. How come I've never met
your family? I don't have one.
I've released him without charge.
No way am I going after someone
like Terry Boyle
because he's the easy way out.
Is everything OK?
I should. um... Yeah.
Good morning.
ALL: Sir.
Thank you. as you were. as you were.
I have authorised an official AC-12
inquiry into Operation Lighthouse.
Gail Vella's murder is this force's
highest-profile investigation.
It will be our job to detect
whether police misconduct
and/or corruption
has contributed to this murder
remaining unsolved.
DS Arnott. Sir.
SIO on Lighthouse is Detective
Chief Inspector Joanne Davidson.
No MIT officers are aware AC-12
is scrutinising Lighthouse.
All information we've harvested
so far has been acquired
from a source on the Hill
known as Officer J.
..to our inquiry.
The CHIS's name
was Alastair Oldroyd. age 22.
Oldroyd was in a pub on the night
of October 26th
and the person calling himself
Ross Turner
gave Oldroyd homophobic abuse.
Turner intimidated Oldroyd
by allegedly boasting of involvement
in Gail Vella's murder.
Sorry. sir. Have you got a sec?
Come in.
You don't need me to tell you
we need a witness to this meeting
between Oldroyd and Turner
to identify whether it was Boyle
or Banks.
Unfortunately. the CHIS lied
about the name of the pub.
Handler believes he was protecting
friends who trade drugs there.
We're checking out establishments
in the vicinity
of Beechwood House for CCTV.
plus local authority cameras
in the area.
just in the hope of identifying
Oldroyd. Banks or Boyle
on the night of the 26th.
Cheers. Chris. Crack on. Boss.
Thanks. Ma'am.
Boss. obviously we've got
to consider
whether Oldroyd's death
was suicide or murder.
Hence we're investigating it.
Yeah. I'm not saying anything
you don't already know. boss.
but if it was murder.
then it raises the question
that someone knew Oldroyd
had info on Gail Vella's death.
I know. I hate to say it. Kate.
but one thing I've learned
over the years -
the fewer coppers in the loop.
the better.
KNOCK AT WINDOW
What's going on with Farida Jatri?
I was about to ask the same. sir.
She's just handed in
a transfer request.
Personal reasons.
She's an experienced PS.
We're at a crucial phase of Vella.
In confidence. sir. I've noticed
some issues with PS Jatri.
What kind of issues?
I don't want to say anything
that might come back to haunt us.
Last thing you need is a tribunal.
What?
I'll draft a glowing reference.
and she'll be some
other station's problem.
You're a life-saver.
Yeah.
Sir. What have you got?
Sir. the team have managed
to pull some Gail Vella reports
from our archive.
Obviously. they all relate to
cases involving AC-12.
REPORTERS: Chief Inspector Osbourne!
Chief Inspector Osbourne!
I take pride
in the courage and professionalism
of my counterterrorism officers.
To say any more
risks prejudicing the inquest.
Thank you.
Chief Inspector!
Official police statements record
counter-terrorism officers
shouted. "Armed police"
and ordered Mr Ali to surrender.
Mr Ali's widow. Aaliyah. insists
there was no warning.
no chance to surrender
before her husband was gunned down
by a hail of bullets.
They lied through their teeth.
every single one of them.
except you. Steve.
I mean. talk about an outrage.
A commanding officer made chief.
If that had happened on my patch...
Jesus.
Next one. Chloe.
NEW VIDEO PLAYS
PROTESTERS SHOUT
A jury found retired Chief
Superintendent Patrick Fairbank
guilty of all charges.
What that jury didn't hear. and
only now am I allowed to report.
are allegations Patrick Fairbank
suppressed police investigations
into child sexual exploitation
that transcended
local political figures
such as Councillor Dale Roach.
It's now a matter of public record
that Jimmy Savile cultivated
relationships
with senior police officers.
Savile exploited those relationships
to intimidate anyone attempting
to investigate his offending.
We now realise what Savile was
getting
out of those relationships
with senior police officers.
What remains unknown
and uninvestigated
is what those officers were getting
out of their relationship
with Savile.
Gail Vella. reporting
from Queen Elizabeth Law Courts.
So Gail Vella drew attention
to alleged links
between organised crime. politicians
and senior police officers.
And these are just the reports
we found in our own archive.
Wee girl killed in cold blood...
..and her killer free as a bird.
Thank you. Chloe. Sir.
Cheers. Chloe. Sarge.
Gaffer. it can't be a coincidence
Carl Banks was a violent offender
involved with organised crime.
Yeah. but if your man pulled
the trigger.
that means he's a gun for hire.
That order came from higher up.
But the question still remains.
what is the motive
for Gail Vella's murder?
All right. she's a controversial
journalist. I'll give you that.
But there's no evidence to suggest
that she dug up anything
that wasn't there before.
Maybe she was working on something
that would.
PHONE RINGS
Superintendent Hastings.
Thanks. Steve. Thanks.
Sir.
Yeah. I'll be right down.
Steph. what are you doing here?
You promised you'd call me back.
It's HMRC.
WHISPERS: Not here. not here.
let's go somewhere private.
Tea. coffee?
No. we're fine. Thanks. though.
Cool. So. have a seat.
Cheers. How can I help you?
I would like to ask you some
questions about Gail Vella.
You were working with her closely
at the time of her death.
Detectives interviewed me a few
days after.
Our department
is conducting further inquiries.
Yeah. I was her producer for a
couple of years.
Well. one line of inquiry is
she fell victim to an obsessed fan.
Do you recall any individuals
that gave Gail cause for concern?
Female journalists get the worst
of it.
from accusations of bias
to threats of sexual violence.
Everything was reported at the time
to our security or to the police.
You say Miss Vella received threats
as a result of her reporting.
Were there any particularly
controversial reports?
Maybe I should just show you.
The Deputy Chief Constable
and I are pleased to report
that Operation Pear Tree has
completed a thorough investigation
into institutionalised complicity
between organised criminals
and corrupt police officers.
Its robust findings
couldn't be clearer.
There is no institutionalised
corruption in this police force.
Operation Pear Tree.
the inquiry described
as the most thorough ever undertaken
into police corruption.
is now officially closed.
Some will wonder why this news
is being announced
over a holiday weekend.
Cynics might conclude the
Police and Crime Commissioner
would prefer his statement
isn't examined too closely.
Perhaps Mr Sindwhani has learned
the secret to high office
appears no longer to reside in
revealing the deepest truths.
but in telling
the most attractive lies.
Gail Vella reporting...
I had to cut that from
the broadcast version.
This is unbroadcast material?
It would never have been released?
Not in this form. no.
She'd seen the success of a podcast
about police corruption
surrounding the murder of a private
detective. Daniel Morgan.
The material Gail couldn't get on
air.
she was funnelling
into a podcast serial of her own.
Where can we access this podcast?
It never got that far.
Gail must not have finished it.
Do you know anything about
the content of this podcast?
I know she was pursuing
several senior police officers for
interview.
She was digging much more deeply
into why there'd been suppression
of police inquiries
into the likes of
Councillor Dale Roach.
Did she keep notes or recordings?
Yeah. What journalist wouldn't?
That's why I suggested Gail's
killer must have stolen them.
Sorry. you disclosed this
to the original murder detectives?
And they said there was no
grounds to suspect a burglary.
This is the first we've heard
of burglary being a factor
in Gail Vella's murder.
Nor was there evidence of a
disturbance inside the property.
The killer stole something.
He knew exactly what he was looking
for and where to find it.
And I'm assuming the original
investigation
seized all of Gail Vella's
electronic devices. Yes. sir.
They were after messages
or threats from an obsessed fan.
Yes. but they weren't looking
at her journalism.
If your theory is right. Steve.
these files could point a finger
at someone
who may have had a motive
to order her murder.
I think those devices
need to be reanalysed.
We'll have to find a way to do that
without alerting Davidson.
Right...
Thank you. Chloe.
Sir.
You're worried about what might
happen to Kate
when Davidson finds
out we're investigating her?
Yes. sir. I get it. son.
I really do. I get it. but...
..Kate has made her bed.
Now she's got to lie in it.
and we have a job to do.
Sir.
Wait. Steve.
I've been giving the situation some
thought.
and loyalty works both ways.
I'm going to have to confirm
it with HR.
but ahead of the formal promotion
process. I am making you a temp DI.
Congratulations. son.
you've earned it.
Thank you. sir.
All right?
All right.
Just like old times.
Yeah.
We're moving forward with Vella.
Moving forward how?
At some point. we're going to hit
the Hill.
Shit. For Christ's sake. Steve...
This is why I got you here.
I can't leave a digital trail.
but I wanted you to know.
Well. why are you involving me?
We've got some leads. but...
Look. Kate. if you can feed me the
inside track on Davidson.
maybe we won't need to show our hand
just yet.
For Christ's sake. Steve. she's my
gaffer. You want me to rat on her?
You're no rat if she's bent.
What am I. then? An honest copper.
Yeah. I'm sure everyone will
see it like that.
Look. Kate. it goes beyond Davidson.
If organised crime ordered
the murder of Gail Vella.
they're protecting Carl Banks
and framing Terry Boyle.
Yeah. we get it.
We're working on it.
Look. I just need to know when.
When is it going to come out that
AC-12 are investigating Davidson?
I've already said too much.
Yeah. likewise.
You always choose
a right shithole.
All right. Chris? Pathologist's
in there now. boss.
Knife wound to the throat.
Looks like the body's been here for
a few days. Witnesses?
It's a long-derelict site with no
security presence and no CCTV.
Highly unlikely we'll harvest
any surveillance images.
Any ID yet?
Matches the appearance
of Carl Banks.
Shit.
Good news. ma'am.
The search team's found a knife.
No apparent blood deposits
on the ground.
but best test for them anyway.
The killer didn't put much effort
into evidence disposal.
DI Fleming. Farida's replacement.
PC Ryan... Pilkington. ma'am.
Pleased to meet you. ma'am.
Don't knock it. Kate.
We're overdue a lucky break.
Thanks. Ryan. Ma'am.
Fingerprints are only a 90% match
due to early decomposition.
but DNA's confirmed the body
is definitely Carl Banks.
Sorry. ma'am. you asked to receive
the forensic report
as soon as it was in.
Thanks. Ryan.
You couldn't do us a cuppa.
could you? I'm gasping.
Yeah. no problem at all. ma'am.
DI Fleming. DS Lomax? I'm fine. ta.
Me too. But...this has been
bugging me.
Have we worked together before?
Did you come and give a talk
at the training college. ma'am?
No.
Thanks. Ryan. Ma'am.
For Christ's sake. Boss?
Fingerprints on the knife found
close to Carl Banks's body
match Alastair Oldroyd. the CHIS.
The pathologist confirmed Banks
died a couple of days earlier.
The timeline works for Oldroyd
to have killed Banks.
Sarge? I mean. sir?
Shit. Sir.
What have you got? Sir.
it's just come up on the Box.
Carl Banks has been found dead.
No more beating about the bush.
We raid Operation Lighthouse. Sir.
I'll put together a team
and transport.
AC-12. DI Arnott.
It's your lawful duty to comply
with my officers. Sir.
DI Arnott. AC-12.
We have the lawful authority to
investigate Operation Lighthouse.
All officers. go to your desks.
You'll each be questioned by an
AC-12 caseworker.
You'll each be obliged
to surrender all materials relating
to Operation Lighthouse
to said caseworkers.
Failure to comply will be a breach
of your duties and responsibilities
under police conduct regulations
and may lead to a misconduct charge
under said regulations. Nobody move.
What the hell's all this about?
On whose authority?
We have a signed authority
from Deputy Chief Constable Wise
to seize all MIT files relating
to the murder of Gail Vella.
Let me see that. Sir. as you know.
wilful obstruction of my officers
executing their lawful duty
is a criminal offence.
DCI Davidson. I notified the DCC
of my concerns
regarding leaking
of confidential police information
such as the operation to arrest
Ross Turner
and the identity of the CHIS who
gave us Turner's name and address.
The DCC agreed to a moratorium
on further distribution
of Operation Lighthouse files
until said information leakage
has been fully investigated.
We'd be the ones to investigate it.
Nonetheless. you'll see the DCC's
authorised me
to withhold
Operation Lighthouse files.
Why didn't the DCC inform
us about this?
To prevent information leakage.
naturally.
No. you did it to make mugs
of AC-12.
That was just an added bonus.
STIFLED LAUGHTER
Priceless!
Let's go. Right. everyone.
let's go.
Cheers. Kate. Nice one.
How did Davidson know?
Give me a minute.
PHONE RINGS
Steve. I'm sorry.
I trusted you. mate.
Look. I'm damned if I do.
I'm damned if I don't.
What was I supposed to do?
Andrea advised me this is
about Operation Lighthouse.
I need to be in the loop.
Well. I am here because AC-12's
lawful investigation
has been unjustly obstructed.
Operation Lighthouse
has had its setbacks. of course.
but your involvement needs to be
correctly handled
so the public
don't leap to the wrong conclusion.
I briefed Andrea
on the required optics.
This isn't an inquiry
into misconduct/corruption.
Well. the investigation
usually precedes the findings.
Clearly. we're all frustrated
Gail Vella's murderer hasn't
been brought to justice yet.
so it makes sense to pitch AC-12's
involvement
as a routine performance review.
Officers of your rank
normally appreciate politics
as much as policing.
Yes.
I'm interested in one thing
and one thing only.
and that's bent coppers.
I hope you'll cooperate.
Superintendent.
Now. apologies -
if you'll excuse me.
I'm due to attend
the Crime Executive. Sir.
Unless there are any outstanding
issues. Ted.
I'm prepared to reissue
the authority
for AC-12 to proceed with your
review of Operation Lighthouse.
It appears my team have been delayed
for nothing better than a PR
briefing. the result of which
is that MIT officers are now aware
of our inquiry
and may be concealing
evidence as we speak.
No-one's concealing evidence. Ted.
They're working their bollocks off
trying to find Gail Vella's killer.
Ma'am.
How'd it go. sir?
Well. we're back in business.
Thank you. sir.
So you make the mess
and I tidy it up.
is that how this goes?
Well. you're not denying it.
so it must have been Officer J
or DI Kate Fleming
who blew the gaff.
I reckon you'd only trust Kate with
this kind of information. yeah?
Well. she's cooked her goose now.
God help her
if she thinks she's going to get
some kind of special treatment from
me.
because she's got another thing
coming. As for DCI Davidson.
she must have had great fun
pulling this stroke.
but she will be laughing
on the other side of her face
when I'm finished with her.
Serve her with a Reg 15.
Sir. Carry on.
DC Bishop. AC-12.
I'm sure you can all guess
what this is about.
I need access to your computer.
Could you stand up. please?
Show me your files. please.
Can I have your password. please?
I need your login details.
What is this document here?
Here you go. sir.
Ma'am. please find enclosed
a Regulation 15 notice
requiring you to attend AC-12
for a formal interview
within the next ten working days.
A copy of this letter has been sent
to your Police Federation
representative.
DOORBELL RINGS
Steve. I was up on a case.
I'm sorry. Steph. I should have
called. No. no. it's fine. Come in.
Tea. isn't it? Yeah. ta.
How are the girls?
Gemma still doesn't get it.
not really.
I'm dreading her not
remembering her daddy.
Well. these will help.
John won't be forgotten.
Thanks for all you did at the time.
You didn't have to.
I'd like to think he'd have done
the same for me.
He died in the line of duty.
Shame the big bosses never saw
it that way.
Sorry. I ought to know - milk
and sugar? Just milk. please.
It's good you were able
to keep the house.
I know you were worried.
Tearing my hair out. more like.
Fortunately.
there was John's life insurance.
Nice TV.
Champions League game's on later.
Not that you lot have got
an interest. Next season.
I didn't know you'd bother
with the sports channels.
It all comes in the package.
Cheap as chips.
Sorry. what am I like? Sit down.
Steve?
It's just a spasm. It'll pass.
You sure?
I've got some painkillers
in the car. I'll just...
Don't move. I'll get them. I'll get
your car keys. Inside pocket.
HE GROANS
I can't believe the DCC
caved so easily.
Sorry. boss.
Not your fault at all.
Thanks for the heads-up.
I know the kind of cases
that AC-12 are into. boss.
Out of work. forget "Boss".
You all right?
This Reg 15...
Yeah. I know how it must feel.
but it's just the way AC-12 operate.
The truth is. it's all getting
a bit tense.
How does it make me look.
investigating a guy with learning
difficulties?
Straight up. Jo.
do you think
he could have killed Gail?
You've been doing this job
long enough to realise
we can never know for sure.
We just gather the evidence.
do our best.
Right now. my best
is nowhere near good enough.
A young woman. could have been you
or me. Kate. her life cut short.
And whoever did it's
got away with it.
and that's my fault.
Do you fancy another?
Ladies? Two more. please.
Can we get those?
Have a good night. guys.
Two more. please.
I'm sorry. Kate.
My self-pity's blown your chances.
Nah. not really my type.
You sure you're OK to drive?
Yeah. sorry about all that earlier.
I'm fine.
The last thing I meant was to put
you out.
Get away. it's just nice to have
some grown-up company for a change.
This a long job?
The case you're up here on?
Could be.
If you're passing again.
don't hesitate.
Don't stay out. it's freezing.
I've got to set the sat-nav
and everything.
Night. Steve. Safe journey.
Night.
Thanks for coming out. Kate.
Sorry to unload my problems.
No worries.
Glad I could be a sounding board.
Well. this is me.
It's Mark's turn to have Josh this
weekend if you're at a loose end.
I'd need to check my diary.
Yeah. no pressure.
My diary's empty.
I've just come out
of a long-term relationship.
I. um...
It would be nice to see
you at the weekend.
Chloe. how's it going?
Davidson gave us full cooperation.
so we've got the lot.
We've recovered Vella's computers
that were seized after her murder.
I thought you'd want to prioritise
them. Great. Hi. Amanda. Hi.
The digital forensics team
have triaged the desktop computer.
the laptop computer. The truth is.
they're remarkably clean.
What do you mean?
All applications still have store
settings. hardly any personal files.
What. they were planted?
Her killer replaced her actual
computers to cover up the burglary?
I'll order the keyboards to be
swabbed and screens fingerprinted.
That way. we can see if Gail ever
even touched them. Good call.
So you've found nothing at all?
The only item of interest is
a tiny audio file.
It appears only partially
downloaded.
How would that happen?
Going with your theory.
it would be when the murderer
installed the replacement devices.
They would have synced to her phone.
momentarily started to import
the audio file before the murderer
broke the link.
That would involve
him knowing her passwords.
Sorry.
GAIL VELLA ON AUDIO FILE:
Savile lied to cover them up.
Some police officers not only
accepted those lies.
they propagated them.
We're losing our power
to challenge lies.
MALE VOICE: There's some people
you can't challenge.
We're losing our power to challenge
lies.
There's some people you can't
challenge.
Sorry. sir. I didn't think
you'd still be here.
We need to find the rest
of Gail's recordings.
Yeah. Amanda said she's on it.
Do you mind me asking. sir.
but why have these been put up?
The gaffer's never going to give it
up.
not as long as he still runs
this place.
And what about you?
What about me?
Well. do you still believe there's
a fourth man out there - H?
I've moved on.
That's us now.
RECORDING DEVICE PLAYS LONG TONE
TONE STOPS
Anti-Corruption Unit 12 interview
of Detective Chief Inspector
Joanne Davidson
in the presence of her Police
Federation representative.
DCI John Rix. by Superintendent
Hastings.
Detective Inspector Arnott
and Detective Constable Bishop.
Ma'am. this interview relates
to Operation Lighthouse.
the inquiry into the murder of Gail
Vella on September 10th. 2019.
on which you've been senior
investigating officer
since 6th October
of that same year.
Document six in your folders.
Document six is a copy of
an incident report
lawfully seized by AC-12
from the offices of the murder
investigation team
located at Hillside Lane Police
Station on 4th November.
Said incident report describes
events
on the morning of 27th October.
specifically the diversion and delay
of an operation
to arrest a suspect
in the murder of Gail Vella
in order to attend an armed robbery
taking place at Hickey's Bookmakers.
Verlaine Road.
On screen. images 11 to 14.
Images 11 to 14 show street views
of said location.
DCI Davidson. can you kindly
explain your actions
on the morning of October 27th
in relation to this armed robbery?
En route to arrest the suspect.
I observed a suspicious vehicle.
Further inquiries detected
an armed robbery in progress.
I ordered my officers to intervene.
DCI Davidson's actions prevented
a serious and immediate threat
to members of the public.
Commendable.
DI Arnott. Image 14 on screen.
Image 14 shows the line of sight
from the route of the MIT convoy
to the location of the
suspicious vehicle.
Given you were a front-facing
passenger.
it was a narrow line of sight.
Plus. you were going
like the clappers.
Nonetheless. I did see the vehicle
and. as a result.
numerous members of the public
were saved from a terrifying ordeal.
Oh.
And what was it about this vehicle?
Sir? I mean. it's just an ordinary
van parked in an ordinary street.
Why give it the time of day?
A registration check
proved suspicious.
Yes. but you only found that out
after you stopped to investigate.
It was an idling MPV parked
adjacent to a bookmakers.
The driver wasn't reading
a newspaper
or messing about on his phone.
His eyes were fixed on the bookies.
He was alert for a quick getaway.
Oh.
And you deduced all that
in the fraction of a second?
Call it a police officer's instinct.
Oh. yes. we all get those from
time to time. DCI Davidson.
I might be getting one right now.
DC Bishop.
We've examined MIT records in
relation to the armed robbery.
Document 12 in your folders
and image 20 on screen.
Image 20 shows the men arrested
in the act of conducting an armed
robbery
of Hickey's Bookmakers
on October 27th.
None of these men has a history
of serious or violent crime.
The robbery took place early
in the morning.
when takings would be at their
lowest.
So what would you deduce
from these facts. DCI Davidson?
A group of amateur criminals
attempted an armed robbery
in an amateur fashion.
According to Murder Investigation
Team files
lawfully seized on 4th November.
attending the armed robbery
on the morning of 27th October
caused a delay of two hours and 25
minutes to the operation planned
to arrest a suspect using the alias
Ross Turner.
believed to reside at Flat 4F.
Beechwood House. Moss Heath.
This delay was out of
DCI Davidson's control.
One of the armed robbers
was shot dead
by an authorised firearms officer.
This necessitated a forensic
deployment and replacement AFOs.
We also understand that an authority
for directed surveillance
applied to Beechwood House.
The required authority
should have been for intrusive
surveillance.
As a result. while the matter
was resolved.
surveillance was absent for a period
of three hours and 35 minutes.
It needed to be resolved.
Any evidence captured
during the wrong authority
would have been inadmissible. Well.
maybe it would have been a good idea
to get the right authority in
the first place. wouldn't you say?
The error in assigning the
wrong surveillance authority
was committed by a senior officer.
That isn't in the file.
I chose not to embarrass him.
Look. DCI Davidson. we are charged
here
with investigating serious crimes.
not least the murder of a young
woman in the prime of her life.
And I expect all policemen and women
to uphold their duty to the public
above any misguided loyalty they may
have to their fellow officers.
Now. who was the senior officer?
No comment. sir.
DI Arnott. will you bookmark
that for the DIR?
Failure to comply.
Sir.
DC Bishop.
Image 29 on screen.
Please refer to document 15
in your folders.
a copy of an arrest report lawfully
seized on 4th of November.
Said arrest report describes
the arrest on 27th October
at Flat 4F Beechwood House
of a person later identified
as Terry Boyle.
shown on the right in image 29.
Also detected at the property
were fingerprints and DNA deposits
matching Carl Banks.
shown on the left in image 29.
Let's start with Terry Boyle.
According to files lawfully seized
on November 4th.
a covert human intelligence source
submitted information to his
handler.
which was communicated to the Murder
Investigation Team via phone call
at 23.21 on 26th October.
The CHIS claimed a person
using the name Ross Turner
had confessed to the murder
of Gail Vella.
Terry Boyle's semen was detected
on images of Gail Vella found
in his permanent residence.
which is located a short
distance from Gail Vella's home.
Also detected at the property
were chemical traces of heroin
and cocaine.
and on an item of outer clothing
particles of gunshot residue.
Incriminating evidence.
Gail Vella's Peugeot 108
was intercepted.
As Miss Vella got out of the
vehicle.
she was murdered with a single
gunshot
carried out using a hard contact
method
in which the muzzle of the pistol
was forced against the back
of Miss Vella's head.
Now. this technique confines
noise and gunshot powder.
The murderer successfully evaded
all neighbourhood security cameras.
These findings strongly suggest
a contract killing
of the type
ordered by organised crime.
Terry Boyle has no criminal record.
no known association with organised
crime.
and suffers from learning
difficulties which raise doubts
regarding his capacity to commit
a cold-blooded assassination.
The finding of images of Gail Vella
suggested Boyle was an obsessed fan.
While the hard contact technique
is associated with contract killing.
it's not exclusive.
There's no physical reason
an amateur couldn't do the same.
The particles of gunshot residue
also link Boyle to the crime.
They're below the threshold
amount you'd expect
if Boyle had been holding the gun.
Then add in the total lack of blood
spatter - there's not even a spot.
That's correct. DI Arnott.
We suspect the coat was
cross-contaminated
from Boyle's hands or other
clothing.
clothing he could have disposed
of after the murder.
That's speculation. ma'am.
You've got no evidence.
Which is why I didn't charge him.
Right. let's take a look at this
fellow Carl Banks.
Image 30 on screen. Image 30 shows
Carl Banks's criminal record.
Banks has a long association
with organised crime
and a history of violence.
including firearms offences.
He fits the profile of a
contract killer.
To use your words. DI Arnott.
that's speculation.
Also. there's the question
of motive.
Terry Boyle fits the profile
of an obsessed fan.
We've never been able to identify
a motive
for a contract killing
against Gail Vella.
There's the possibility Vella
was working on an explosive story.
Not only was she executed.
her research was stolen.
A desktop and laptop computer
recovered from the property
and recently re-examined bear no
fingerprints
or DNA deposits matching Gail Vella.
We believe these items were planted
to conceal a burglary.
That's not in our files.
No. but it's in ours.
We're detectives. too. you know.
in case you hadn't noticed.
DCI Davidson has led an exemplary
inquiry.
If you've got new information.
you should share it with
the Murder Investigation Team.
According to your files.
fingerprints and DNA deposits
matching Banks
detected at Beechwood House
were far more numerous
than those matching Boyle.
suggesting Banks was
the primary resident.
and also detected at Beechwood House
were signs of forced entry.
Image 37 on screen is
from Carl Banks's postmortem.
Document 21 in your folders
is a copy of the postmortem report.
According to said postmortem
report. the pathologist concluded
Carl Banks died from exsanguination
due to a deep laceration
to the neck.
most likely inflicted by a knife.
Also detected on Banks's body
were lacerations and bruising
caused by heavy blunt trauma
to the head.
facial lacerations and bruising.
and lesions on both wrists
consistent with ligature restraints.
All these injuries were caused some
time before his death.
and time of death was put at
on or around 27th October.
So. what we have here is a forced
entry into Carl Banks's flat.
Banks beaten unconscious.
his hands tied and.
some time later. his throat cut.
None of this could have occurred
without his arrest being delayed
and the surveillance being absent.
Now. call me suspicious.
DCI Davidson. but it seems to me
that somebody got wind
that Banks was shooting his mouth
off about Vella's murder
and they decided to murder him
to stop him talking.
Not only that. but they knew
that your team was on course
to arrest him.
They knew the route you were taking.
And to top it all. they knew
the surveillance was absent.
so that meant they could walk
in there.
drag Banks out
and substitute him with Terry Boyle.
And none of this.
none of this could have happened
without you. and you alone. spotting
that van outside the bookies
and deciding for some reason
I cannot fathom
that it warranted investigation.
Sir. all this is circumstantial.
There's no evidence to support
anyone knowing any details
of Operation Lighthouse.
Evidence? We'll give you evidence.
DC Bishop.
Image 41. Image 41 shows
item reference AR-6.
a knife that was detected in
the vicinity of Carl Banks's body.
Yeah. the killer. he didn't even
bother
to throw the knife into the canal.
I mean. he left it lying around
for the search team to find.
That was handy. wasn't it?
Criminals make mistakes.
That's how we catch them.
I could say exactly the same.
DCI Davidson. exactly the same.
Please refer to document 23
in your folders.
a copy of a forensic report on item
reference AR-6.
Blood detected on AR-6 was subjected
to DNA analysis.
The DNA harvested from blood cells
on AR-6
match with 99.9% probability
DNA from Carl Banks.
Fingerprints on AR-6 match
with 99.9% probability
fingerprints belonging
to Alastair Oldroyd.
Alastair Oldroyd was the CHIS
who submitted the original intel
that Banks had confessed
to Vella's murder.
So. for some reason.
Alastair Oldroyd.
no history of violent crime.
kills Banks.
The evidence proves Oldroyd
handled the murder weapon.
We suspect Banks had been
threatening Oldroyd.
Are you trying to kid us that
Alastair Oldroyd went in there.
beat Banks unconscious.
dragged him out of the fla...?
He was ten stone wringing wet!
And that's not the half of it.
not by a long chalk. DI Arnott.
Document 31.
According to your files.
Oldroyd was found dead
on 29th October
from a fall from the derelict
Chapel Place Car Park.
According to said files.
due to the lack of witnesses
and security cameras.
it's impossible to determine
if Oldroyd jumped or he was pushed.
Our hypothesis is that Oldroyd
killed Banks.
then committed suicide.
Yeah. your hypothesis.
So there we have it.
a series of suspicious deaths
that conveniently obliterate a trail
of evidence that might lead us
to Gail Vella's actual murderer.
And in the meantime.
you have that wee fella Terry Boyle
on police bail.
You have failed to consider
the alternative.
that Carl Banks murdered Gail Vella
on the orders of organised crime.
that organised criminals murdered
Carl Banks for his silence.
and that organised criminals framed
Alastair Oldroyd for Banks's murder
and then staged Oldroyd's murder
to look like a suicide.
Of course I've considered
alternatives...
And none of this. none of this would
have happened
without crucial information
on police activities
being leaked to organised crime.
I agree.
Excuse me?
I agree. sir.
If your theory is correct. the only
way it could have worked
would have been for a corrupt
officer from my team
to have leaked
key information to organised crime.
Well. as I'm sure you're aware of.
DCI Davidson.
there's really only
one way we're going to find out.
DCI Joanne Davidson.
you do not have to say anything.
but it may harm your defence if
you do not mention when questioned
something you later rely on
in court.
Anything you do say
may be used in evidence.
DCI Davidson. did you leak
information
on your team's operations?
No. sir. I did not.
Do you know of anyone who did leak
information?
No. sir. I do not.
I'd ask if you've examined
my communications history.
As per anti-corruption powers.
we've been able to access
your work calls and e-mails.
Any evidence that I've been
communicating with an OCG?
No. ma'am. However. we all recognise
that such communication is
typically carried out
by unregistered so-called
burner phones.
I don't have a burner phone.
Search my address. search my car.
We will. ma'am.
Fine.
Are we done. sir?
No. DCI Davidson.
we are not done here.
I'm not happy with some
of the answers
you've given
in this interview today.
Specifically. I'm concerned
about three unanswered questions.
One. your possible collusion
in diverting and delaying
Carl Banks's arrest.
Two. your possible collusion
in the failure to maintain constant
surveillance on Carl Banks's flat.
And three. your possible
collusion in leaking information
regarding items one and two.
And so. therefore. DCI Davidson.
I'm going to arrest you on suspicion
of perverting the course of justice.
DCI Davidson strenuously denies the
allegations...
You will be held here
until we can find a suitable
police custody cell.
Interview terminated at 11.22.
Wait.
An OCG needed time to plan the
robbery and the abduction of Banks.
If I was SIO on this.
the first thing I'd want to know
is who knew about Banks's confession
early enough.
In order. that's the CHIS handler.
then my officers who received
his call. PS Jatri and DS Lomax.
then me. then my boss.
Detective Superintendent Buckells.
If you're going to search my home.
I'd suggest you search theirs too.
Do you understand how much work I've
got to do?
When the Chief Super phones up
and asks what's going on
with Lighthouse. right.
what am I going to tell him?
Cheers. guys. Oh. about bloody
time.
You want to tell me what the hell's
going on?
Detective Superintendent Buckells.
in connection with our lawful
inquiry into Operation Lighthouse.
we have received authority to
examine the communications activity
of certain named officers.
Is this a piss-take or what?
Sir. your work and personal
communications records
are currently being scrutinised.
Furthermore. we have received
authority to carry out a search
of your vehicle and your home
under warrant powers.
This is a joke.
a total pigging joke.
Well. yeah. I'll tell you what.
when you find my stash of jazz mags.
feel free to knock one out.
Thank you for your cooperation. sir.
PHONE RINGS
DI Arnott.
It's Chloe. sir.
Look. I'm at the search
and the FIs have found
a cache of burner phones.
Where? Davidson's?
No. Officer J's.
At Farida's.
On my way.
SIREN WAILS
For the DIR. I'm showing PS Jatri
item reference CB-4.
CB-4 is an unregistered
mobile phone
detected during a lawful search
of 29 Stalton Drive.
Do you recognise this phone?
No.
For the DIR. I'm showing PS Jatri
image 76.
Image 76 shows a cache of similar
devices
detected during said lawful
search of 29 Stalton Drive.
How do you account for these devices
being found hidden in your home?
They've been put there!
I don't know anything about them.
All these devices bear DNA deposits
matching your elimination
samples.
I've never even seen them
before. let alone touched them!
Examination of mobile phone CB-4
reveals calls made in the early
hours of October 27th
to an unidentified number.
The timing of these calls
coincides exactly
with the first intelligence report
of a suspect claiming to have
murdered Gail Vella.
Did you pass on confidential
information
on the operation to arrest
this suspect?
No. no! I had nothing
to do with it!
Farida Jatri. I have been
in consultation
with the Crown Prosecutor
and she has authorised me to charge
you with the following offences...
I'm being framed!
Who's framing you?
Who are you claiming is framing you?
It's Jo. it's Jo Davidson.
She planted those phones.
You're claiming she broke
into your house?
She didn't have to break in.
What do you mean by that?
She lived there with me.
We searched DCI Davidson's home
address. It appeared lived in.
Yeah. she has her own place. she
just keeps overnight stuff at mine.
We found no items belonging
to another person.
She moved out.
Are you able to disclose to us
the nature of this relationship?
She was lying to me.
She lied and lied.
That's the kind of person she is.
None of you know what she's like.
SHE SOBS
God give me strength.
I don't know who to believe.
Well. now it seems possible Farida
made allegations about Davidson
for personal reasons. But the stuff
we've found since then...
Isn't enough. Not yet. anyway.
HE TAPS AT PHONE
Superintendent Hastings.
Release DCI Davidson.
Why won't anyone believe me?
Thanks. I'm fine from here. Ma'am.
Where to. ma'am?
I need to pick up my car.
I don't know if they've told you
about PS Jatri...
That's what happens to a rat.
SHE SOBS
SHE WAILS